Explain in detail:

● HDFS:
• HDFS is Hadoop Distributed File System. HDFS provides scalable, fault-tolerant storage at low cost.
• The HDFS software detects and compensates for hardware issues, including disk problems and server failure.
• HDFS stores files across the collection of servers in a cluster.
• Files are decomposed into blocks and each block is written to more than one of the servers.
• The replication provides both fault-tolerance and performance.
  HDFS has been designed keeping in view the following features:
• Very large files: Files that are megabytes, gigabytes, terabytes. or petabytes in size.
• Streaming data access: HDFS is built around the idea that data is written once, but read many times.
• A dataset is copied from the source and then analysis is done on that dataset over time.
• Commodity hardware: Hadoop does not require expensive, highly reliable hardware as it is designed to run on clusters of commodity hardware.
 
● Hadoop cluster:
• Data Storage has grown exponentially in the recent past, but data reading speed has not improved radically.
Data Read Speed were:
In 1990, 1400 MB of data having transfer speed as 4.5 MB/s took 5minutes.
In 2010, 1 TB of data having transfer speed as 100 MB/s took 3hours.
But, with Hadoop clusters in the year 2013, 1TB of data in 100 drives took only 2minutes.
● HDFS Blocks:
• Hard Disk has concentric circles which form tracks.
• One file can contain many blocks
• These blocks in a local file system are nearly 512 bytes and are not necessarily continuous.
• For HDFS, since it is designed for large files, block size is 128 MB by default.
• Moreover, it gets blocks of local file system contiguously to minimise head seek time.

For example, Consider a file of size 400MB then,
3 blocks of 128MB each and
1 block of 16MB will be created.